Guide to the O'Keeffe at Abiquiu.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
O'Keeffe at Abiquiu.
1978-1981
YCAL MSS 263
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.02
(4 boxes)
Photographs created by Myron Wood that document the homes and activities of artist Georgia O'Keeffe in Abiquiu, New Mexico, 1978-1981. Images include interiors and exteriors of the O'Keeffe residence in the village of Abiquiu and her summer home at Ghost Ranch and objects within them. The collection includes portraits of O'Keeffe, her acquaintances, including her gardener Estiben Suazo and his daughter and her maid, Candalaria Suazo, as well as her manager Juan Hamilton.
Wood, Myron, 1921-1999
Patten, Christine Taylor, 1940-
Patten, Christine Taylor, 1940- ( O'Keeffe at Abiquiu)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Sharon Keim on the Martin Greenblatt Foundation Book Fund in American Literature, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Most of the photographs in this collection appeared in Myron Wood and Christine Taylor Patten, O'Keeffe at Abiquiu (New York: Harry N. Abrams, 1995).
Myron Wood (1921-1999)
Myron Wood was a photographer and Assistant Curator of Photography at The Taylor Museum of the Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center from 1951 to 1961and the photographer for Colorado College for over thirty-five years.
Scope and Contents
Photographs created by Myron Wood that document the homes and activities of artist Georgia O'Keeffe in Abiquiu, New Mexico, 1978-1981. Images include interiors and exteriors of the O'Keeffe residence in the village of Abiquiu and her summer home at Ghost Ranch and objects within them. The collection includes portraits of O'Keeffe, her acquaintances, including her gardener Estiben Suazo and his daughter and her maid, Candalaria Suazo, as well as her manager Juan Hamilton.
Arrangement
Photographs in the collection are arranged in the order the images appear in Myron Wood and Christine Taylor Patten, O'Keeffe at Abiquiu (New York: Harry N. Abrams, 1995), this consists of images in the book and an image from the back of the dust jacket, followed by images that did not appear in the work, which are arranged alphabetically by their title.
Ghost Ranch (Abiquiu, N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Abiquiu (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Photographic prints; Hamilton, Juan, 1945- -- Portraits; O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1887-1986 -- Portraits; O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1887-1986 -- Homes and haunts -- New Mexico -- Abiquiu; Patten, Christine Taylor, 1940- ( O'Keeffe at Abiquiu); Suazo, Candalaria -- Portraits; Suazo, Estiban, 1900-1982 -- Portraits; Wood, Myron, 1921-1999; Wood, Myron, 1921-1999 ( O'Keeffe at Abiquiu)
- Photographs, 1978-1981; Series I; 54 photographic prints on 35.6 x 43.2 cm mounts
  General note
  The location for all of the images (except where noted) depict the residence of Georgia O'Keeffe in Abiquiu, New Mexico.
  - Palette, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 15.9 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Location: Abiquiu, New Mexico
    Book Caption: Miss O'Keeffe's Palette. (page 4-5)
  - Small rock, 1980; Photographic print, 14.6 x 24.2 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Book Caption: Stone. The rock seemed to me like an animal skull, suggesting that things are not as they seem. (page 6)
  - O'Keeffe with Sculpture and Painting, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 19.1 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Book Caption: In the Studio. O'Keeffe's intense gaze was penetrating. (page 8)
  - O'Keeffe Sculpture Through Window, 1980; Photographic print, 19.1 x 24.2 cm. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Book Caption: Stoa. A stoa is a Greek architectural term for columns in front of an opening. (page 9)
  - O'Keeffe Resting, 1980; Photographic print, 9.6 x 16.6 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Book Caption: Napping in the Afternoon Sun. Often Miss O'Keeffe's dogs, Inca and Jingo, would join her in a siesta. (page 11)
  - Gardener, 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 24.2 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Book Caption: Gardener Estiben Suazo. Estiben (called Steven by Miss O'Keeffe) looked after the garden and did many household chores. When I showed her this photograph she said, "That sweet old thing." (page 16)
  - O'Keeffe and Juan Hamilton, 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 23.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Book Caption: Miss O'Keeffe and Juan Hamilton. With its two skylights, the living room had perfect light. Juan suggested the picture, put two chairs together, and as he and Miss O'Keeffe sat their body gestures mirrored one another. (page 17)
  - Black Door, Snow, 1980; Photographic print, 15.3 x 19.1 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Book Caption: Magic Snowfall. Miss O'Keeffe said the reason she bought the house was the black door. (page 18)
  - Ladder, 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 22.9 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Book Caption: Ladder after Light Snow. In the manner of traditional New Mexican pueblos, a simple ladder leans against an outside wall. (page 29)
  - Chow, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 15.3 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Book Caption: Inca. An old Japanese saying asserts that "Snow is a grandmother to the dog." (page 30)
  - Snowfall, 1980; Photographic print, 23.5 x 14.6 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Book Caption: Transformation. Soft, large flakes of a typical early spring snowfall sifted gently down. (page 32)
  - Snowy Courtyard with Ladder, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 16.2 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Book Caption: After a Light Snow. The window in the background looks to me like a painting. (page 33)
  - Snow-covered shrub and antlers, 1980; Photographic print, 19.1 x 22.9 cm. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Book Caption: March Snow. Miss O'Keeffe told me with a chuckle that she was always afraid that the horns above the doorway would one day fall on her. (page 35)
  - O'Keeffe Walking, 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 23.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Book Caption: North Courtyard. Miss O'Keeffe walked regularly in the New Mexican sunlight. (page 36)
  - Door and Bench, 1980; Photographic print, 14.6 x 24.2 cm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Book Caption: Bench Corner. A droll example of disrespect for architectural tradition. (page 38)
  - Rear of Entrance, 1980; Photographic print, 10.5 x 17.8 cm. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Book Caption: The Gate. Rays of sun seemed to burn a pattern in this doorway. (page 39)
  - Garden, Dark Window, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 15.0 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Book Caption: North Garden Wall. Abstraction is seen through the wall to the garden. (page 40)
  - Courtyard Door, 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 24.2 cm. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Book Caption: Shadow. Handwrought architecture leaves much for the eye to discover. (page 41)
  - Door and Antlers, 1981; Photographic print, 21.6 x 16.6 cm. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Location: Ghost Ranch, Abiquiu, New Mexico
    Book Caption: Recuerdos (Memories). Cracks in the adobe wall mirror the patterns of the bones. (page 42)
  - Bones and Firewood, 1981; Photographic print, 23.5 x 15.9 cm. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Book Caption: Backbone. The wooden shelf that the bones rested on at Ghost Ranch ran like a backbone through the photograph. (page 44-45)
  - Elk Horns, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 15.9 cm. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Book Caption: Elk Horns in a Passageway. These horns hung in the zaguan, a passage between the main entrance and the patio. Miss O'Keeffe told me that Estiben, for want of anything to do, once carved his initials on the back of the horns, much to her dismay. (page 47)
  - Interior Doorway, 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 24.2 cm. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Book Caption: Fractured Sunlight. The door leads from the Indian room into the roofless room. (page 48)
  - Bodes Calendar, 1980; Photographic print, 15.3 x 22.9 cm. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Book Caption: The Indian Room. When I made this photograph the calendar was rustling in the breeze; I took a clothespin from the basket to keep it still. It was the only object I moved or added in all the photographs I made at Miss O'Keeffe's house. (page 55)
  - Interior Court with Pot, 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 23.5 cm. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Book Caption: In the Roofless Room. Shadows from overhead gave the black pot an elegant setting. (page 57)
  - Paining and Cushions, 1980; Photographic print, 17.8 x 22.6 cm. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Book Caption: Pansies and Forget-Me-Nots, 1927. A wall with a banco (bench) in the living room. (page 65)
  - Calder Mobile, Fireplace, 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 24.2 cm. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Book Caption: Mobile by Alexander Calder. Estiben's arrangement of firewood ready for lighting has its own beauty. (page 69)
  - Rattlesnake Skeleton, 1980; Photographic print, 17.8 x 13.4 cm. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Book Caption: Rattlesnake Skeleton. This skeleton was displayed in a glass-covered inset in the adobe back of the living room. (page 70)
  - M's Fan a gift from Miss O'Keeffe, 1978; Photographic print, 24.2 x 17.8 cm. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Book Caption: Feather Fan. The fan reminded me of the range of tones in O'Keeffe's paintings. (page 71)
  - Wall Cove, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 15.9 cm.; 2 photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
    Book Caption: Wall Cove with Treasures. I printed this negative so that the shape of the niche barely appears in the stark white wall. (page 73)
  - Small Living room, Fireplace, 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 23.5 cm. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Book Caption: Living Room Wall Fireplace. Another instance of Estiben's handiwork. (page 74)
  - Dining Room Fireplace, 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 24.2 cm. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Book Caption: Corner Fireplace in the Dining Room. The massive hearthstone is crowned by Estiben's beautifully laid fire. (page 75)
  - "Daffodils, Dining Room", 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 24.2 cm. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Book Caption: Daffodils and the Corner Fireplace. I was struck by the contrast of the delicate flowers against the rough plywood tabletop. (page 75)
  - Garden and Rock Abiquiu, 1980; Photographic print, 15.9 x 24.2 cm. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Book Caption: Rock as Prototype. The earth shape of this rock echoes a form that O'Keeffe painted time and again. Some rocks in the garden were moved from season to season. This one never moved. (page 76)
  - Garden In Snow, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 14.0 cm. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Book Caption: Winter Garden. I photographed these massive stump forms in the snow to find the strongest relationship with the lacy background. (page 88-89)
  - Iris, 1980; Photographic print, 8.9 x 14.3 cm. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Book Caption: Iris. Irises grew profusely in the garden. (page 90)
  - D. H. Lawrence's Horse, 1980; Photographic print, 16.6 x 24.2 cm. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Book Caption: D. H. Lawrence's Horse. Miss O'Keeffe laughingly referred to this skull, which she found on the Taos ranch where the novelist lived, as "D. H. Lawrence's horse." (page 91)
  - Well Head Cover, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 15.9 cm. (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Book Caption: Wellhead Cover. Miss O'Keeffe and Estiben played a kind of chess with these stones. As they passed by, one person would make a move and the other would respond later, or the next day. (page 92-93)
  - Dried Corn Stalks, 1979; Photographic print, 24.2 x 15.9 cm. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Book Caption: Mulch Pile. I looked at these stalks for a long time, finding order in the designs and earthen tones. (page 94-95)
  - South Wall, 1980; Photographic print, 23.5 x 18.5 cm. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Book Caption: Fantastic Landscape. Water from snow melting on the roof and seeping up from the garden floor creates an otherworldly impression of mountains and village buildings. (page 97)
  - The Sheets, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 14.6 cm. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Book Caption: Among the Sheets. Estiben's daughter, Candalaria, was Miss O'Keeffe's housekeeper. (page 99)
  - Ghost Ranch, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 15.9 cm. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Book Caption: O'Keeffe House at Ghost Ranch. This is the house that the painter first occupied when she moved to New Mexico; the setting inspired many paintings. Miss O'Keeffe often climbed to the roof of this house to paint the glorious cliffs. (page 111)
  - Campo Santo, 1978; Photographic print, 15.9 x 22.9 cm. (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Location: Medanales, New Mexico
    Book Caption: The Old Cemetery. (page 115)
  - Chimneys, 1980; Photographic print, 8.9 x 13.4 cm. (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Book Caption: Chimneys. The surface of the rough adobe and the adze marks on the lintel attest to the handwork of local architecture. (page 117)
  - Rio Grande, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 12.7 cm. (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Book Caption: The Gorge. The Rio Grande River as it flows near Taos, New Mexico. (page 118)
  - Courtyard, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 14.0 cm. (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Book Caption: Stones on the wellhead cover were used like chess pieces by O'Keeffe and her gardener, Estiben; the moved them almost every day. (Back of Dust Jacket)
  - Canyon Pool, 1978; Photographic print, 24.2 x 19.1 cm. (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Not in Book
  - Formal Entrance, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 13.4 cm. (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Great Tree, 1978; Photographic print, 17.8 x 24.2 cm. (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - "Great Tree in Garden, Snow", 1980; Photographic print, 16.6 x 24.2 cm. (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Living Room Fireplace, 1980; Photographic print, 16.2 x 24.2 cm. (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - O'Keeffe, 1980; Photographic print, 22.6 x 13.7 cm. (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - The Gardener's Signature, 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 15.3 cm. (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - "Twigs, Wall and Snow", 1980; Photographic print, 24.2 x 15.3 cm. (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Myron Wood and Christine Taylor Patten, O'Keeffe at Abiquiu (New York: Harry N. Abrams), 1995 (Box 4)